<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4001/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4001/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-04-08T09:50:34-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4001/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Science Mom</title><subtitle>Science Mom, Hands-on Science Curriculum
</subtitle><author><name>Jenny Ballif</name></author><entry><title type="html">Cabbage Lemonade?!? Yes, *pH*lease!</title><link href="http://localhost:4001/Cabbage-Lemonade-Yes-pHlease" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cabbage Lemonade?!? Yes, *pH*lease!" /><published>2021-04-08T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-04-08T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4001/Cabbage-Lemonade-Yes-pHlease</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4001/Cabbage-Lemonade-Yes-pHlease">&lt;h1 id=&quot;cabbage-lemonade-yes-phlease&quot;&gt;Cabbage Lemonade?!? Yes, &lt;em&gt;pH&lt;/em&gt;lease!&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;an-edible-experiment&quot;&gt;An Edible Experiment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cabbage is great in cole slaw, but did you know it’s also perfect for a sweet, tasty, science experiment? Find out how pigments in red cabbage change color in different solutions!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ages: 5 and up (with a parent helping)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img align=&quot;left&quot; src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/eForl3v.jpg&quot; width=&quot;40%&quot; class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; alt=&quot;lemonade and other liquids in glass jars, from above&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/eh95P78.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; alt=&quot;lemonade and other liquids in glass jars, from above&quot; /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-do-it&quot;&gt;How to do it!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;materials-what-youll-need&quot;&gt;Materials (What you’ll need)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
&lt;img style=&quot;float: right&quot; src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/N4rIJEa.jpg&quot; width=&quot;40%&quot; class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; alt=&quot;Supplies to make Cabbage lemonade: water, lemons, red cabbage, sugar&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the lemon juice:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;4 lemons, juiced&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1/2 cup sugar&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 pitcher full of water&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the cabbage water:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 cup chopped cabbage&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2 cups water &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;method-what-to-do&quot;&gt;Method (What to do)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mix lemon juice ingredients together. Use more or less sugar or lemon juice to taste.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boil cabbage and 2 cups of water together. Drain the water and let it cool. Admire its lovely purple color.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Add a few spoonfuls of cabbage water to your lemonade, and watch the color change to pink!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, you can drink your natural pink lemonade! Just be careful not to add too much cabbage water, unless you want your lemonade to smell a bit…. vegetable-y.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-it-works&quot;&gt;How it works:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Purple cabbage gets its gorgeous blue-purple color from a type of pigment molecule called an anthocyanin (AN-tho-SY-uh-nin). Anthocyanins change color depending on the pH of the solutions they’re in. They’re blue or purple in neutral conditions (like water), greenish in alkaline solutions (like water with baking soda in it), and pinkish in acidic solutions (like our lemonade in this experiment).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anthocyanins are found in many plants – berries like blueberries and raspberries, grains like blue corn and black rice, and even in black beans! Scientists aren’t quite sure what they do in plants, but it may help them with resistance to colder temperatures.
You can find out about another important plant pigment, chlorophyll, in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0MzcwgDffrI&quot;&gt;this video&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jenny Ballif</name></author><category term="science activities" /><summary type="html">Cabbage Lemonade?!? Yes, pHlease!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Chladni Plate - make sounds you can see!</title><link href="http://localhost:4001/chladni-plates" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Chladni Plate - make sounds you can see!" /><published>2021-03-11T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-03-11T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4001/chladni-plates</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4001/chladni-plates">&lt;h1 id=&quot;chladni-plate---make-sounds-you-can-see&quot;&gt;Chladni Plate - make sounds you can see!&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/pWe5mfn.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; alt=&quot;A balloon stretched over a cylinder with salt forming a pattern on top&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure it’s fun to listen to sounds, but what if you could see them too? A Chladni plate (pronounced clad-nee) converts sound vibrations to cool patterns on a taut surface, such as a stretched balloon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ages: 3 and up (with a parent helping)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/A6GE9mR.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; alt=&quot;Supplies to make a Chladni plate: oatmeal container, rubber band, balloon, paper towel tube&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-do-it&quot;&gt;How to do it!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;materials-what-youll-need&quot;&gt;Materials (What you’ll need)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A big cylinder (something like an oatmeal canister works great)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a smaller cylinder (like a paper towel tube)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A balloon (If available, use large 18-inch balloons)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tape (duct tape is great)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Knife or scissors&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Salt&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;method-what-to-do&quot;&gt;Method (What to do)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cut a hole the size of your smaller tube into the side of your large cylinder or container. It’s OK if it isn’t perfect!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stick the smaller tube in the hole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cut the neck off the balloon and then stretch your balloon over the top of the large cylinder, and tape it in place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tip: before cutting your balloon, inflate the balloon and let the air out a couple of times to stretch it out. The larger the balloon, the easier it will be to get it over the container.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/riaJqSe.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; alt=&quot;A side view of a Chladni plate.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;You can use lots of different materials to build your Chladni plate.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sprinkle salt over the top of the balloon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speak or sing into the smaller tube, and watch patterns form on the balloon!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can try it with different shapes too. Try using an empty milk carton with the top cut off instead of an oatmeal container to make a square plate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-it-works&quot;&gt;How it works:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sounds are vibrations. The stretched out balloon vibrates differently when different sound waves hit it. Test it out! See if singing or speaking in a low voice makes patterns that are different from ones when you sing in a high squeaky voice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/yaPK6T2.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; alt=&quot;Ernst Chladni and an illustration of the Chladni plate technique&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Ernst Chladni and an illustration of the Chladni plate technique. Both images are public domain.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fun-fact&quot;&gt;Fun Fact:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The physicist Ernst Chladni (1756-1857) who invented the Chladni plate was also really interested in meteorites. He even has a mineral found primarily in meteorites named after him (chladniite, first described in 1993).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Connections to Next Generation Science Standards:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;NGSS 1-PS4-1 Sound vibrates matter&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;NGSS 1-PS4-2 Vibrating matter makes sound&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Jenny Ballif</name></author><category term="science activities" /><summary type="html">Chladni Plate - make sounds you can see!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Science Mom’s Guide to Water, Part 7</title><link href="http://localhost:4001/science-mom-s-guide-to-water-part-7" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Science Mom’s Guide to Water, Part 7" /><published>2018-05-22T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-05-22T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4001/science-mom-s-guide-to-water-part-7</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4001/science-mom-s-guide-to-water-part-7">&lt;h1 id=&quot;science-moms-guide-to-water-part-7&quot;&gt;Science Mom’’s Guide to Water, Part 7&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s finally here! The concluding installment in the water series, a look at evaporative cooling, changes of state, and how water has an impressively high specific heat capacity:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
html,body        {height:100%;}
.vidwrapper      {width:100%; max-width: 600px; height:100%; margin:0 auto; background:#CCC; text-align: center}
.h_iframe        {position:relative; padding-top: 56%;}
.h_iframe iframe {position:absolute;top:0;left:0;width:100%; height:100%;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;vidwrapper&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;h_iframe&quot;&gt;
        &lt;iframe height=&quot;400&quot; width=&quot;2&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/0gqXZJtXgmg&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Out of all the little cartoons I made for various properties of water (which were explored in the first six videos), High Specific Heat is my favorite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;style&gt;
.image-wrapper{
  max-width:90%;
  height:auto;
  display:block;
  margin: auto;
}

.image-wrapper img{
  height:auto;
  display:block;
  text-align: center;
  margin: auto;
  max-width: 100%; 
}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.github.com/jennyballif/jennyballif.github.io/master/images/SMG1/SMG1c.png&quot; alt=&quot;Water's properties of cohesion, adhesion, and surface tension.&quot; style=&quot;width:600px !important&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
.image-wrapper{
  max-width:90%;
  height:auto;
  display:block;
  margin: auto;
}

.image-wrapper img{
  height:auto;
  display:block;
  text-align: center;
  margin: auto;
  max-width: 100%; 
}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.github.com/jennyballif/jennyballif.github.io/master/images/SMG1/SMG1e.png&quot; alt=&quot;Cartoon depiction of water having capillary action and ice being less dense than liquid water.&quot; style=&quot;width:600px !important&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
.image-wrapper{
  max-width:90%;
  height:auto;
  display:block;
  margin: auto;
}

.image-wrapper img{
  height:auto;
  display:block;
  text-align: center;
  margin: auto;
  max-width: 100%; 
}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.github.com/jennyballif/jennyballif.github.io/master/images/SMG1/SMG1d.png&quot; alt=&quot;Cartoon depiction of water being universal solvent and having a high specific heat.&quot; style=&quot;width:600px !important&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I first started my YouTube channel, I had an outline of a dozen videos I wanted to make. I’d planned to have 4 to 7 science experiments in each video and group them by topic. There was the series about water, with seven videos. There was a unit on eggs, milk, hydrogen peroxide, various aspects of physics… you get the idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it didn’t take too many videos for me to realize that this wasn’t the ideal approach. Partly because the scope made each video such a big project (120 plus hours of work) that I procrastinated getting started on them, partly because it was challenging to fit the material within a 15 minute video timeframe, and partly because grouping experiments by subject like this left out quite a few gems that stood more or less on their own. So going forward, “Science Guides” like this are going to be the exception rather than the norm. I plan to have weekly science experiment videos that tackle a single experiment (rather than five of them). So watch for those.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And last, but certainly not least, see below to download your own copy of the foldable book:&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jenny Ballif</name></author><category term="science experiments" /><category term="water" /><category term="heat" /><category term="science" /><category term="experiment" /><summary type="html">Science Mom’’s Guide to Water, Part 7</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Science Mom’s Guide to Water, Part 6</title><link href="http://localhost:4001/science-mom-s-guide-to-water-part-6" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Science Mom’s Guide to Water, Part 6" /><published>2017-09-26T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-09-26T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4001/science-mom-s-guide-to-water-part-6</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4001/science-mom-s-guide-to-water-part-6">&lt;h1 id=&quot;science-moms-guide-to-water-part-6&quot;&gt;Science Mom’’s Guide to Water, Part 6&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Part 5 of the water series we learned that although water is called the “Universal Solvent,” it doesn’t dissolve oil. But what about the things water can dissolve? In Science Mom’s Guide to Water, Part 6, we explore what dissolves in water with several crystal growing activities:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
html,body        {height:100%;}
.vidwrapper      {width:100%; max-width: 600px; height:100%; margin:0 auto; background:#CCC; text-align: center}
.h_iframe        {position:relative; padding-top: 56%;}
.h_iframe iframe {position:absolute;top:0;left:0;width:100%; height:100%;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;vidwrapper&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;h_iframe&quot;&gt;
        &lt;iframe height=&quot;400&quot; width=&quot;2&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/5pAuxot2sEY&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like I mentioned in the above video, we went through those six activities really quickly – particularly the last two. So here are a few quick tips, as well as notes on each activity and an additional short video:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tip 1: The slower the crystal growth, the larger the size of the crystals&lt;/strong&gt;. There are two ways you can slow the growth: by having a less concentrated solution, or by having the temperature decrease more slowly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
.image-wrapper{
  max-width:90%;
  height:auto;
  display:block;
  margin: auto;
}

.image-wrapper img{
  height:auto;
  display:block;
  text-align: center;
  margin: auto;
  max-width: 100%; 
}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.github.com/jennyballif/jennyballif.github.io/master/images/SMG6/temper.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Pouring a spoonful of hot liquid into the glass first.&quot; style=&quot;width:600px !important&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you pour your solution into a glass jar when it’s very hot, BE SURE TO TEMPER THE GLASS FIRST. Do this by adding just one spoonful of hot liquid and swirling it around the bottom of the jar. This heats the glass so it doesn’t break when you add the rest of the liquid. Hot water in the jar will cool more slowly than it would in the pot. The pot conducts heat very efficiently and the water is also more spread out and has a larger surface area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to grow larger size crystals then you’ll either want to put the solution into the container when it’s still very hot, or reduce the amount of solute you use and wait longer for crystal growth. If, on the other hand, you want a smaller size of crystal, then you’ll want to let the solution cool down in the pot before adding it to the jar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
.image-wrapper{
  max-width:90%;
  height:auto;
  display:block;
  margin: auto;
}

.image-wrapper img{
  height:auto;
  display:block;
  text-align: center;
  margin: auto;
  max-width: 100%; 
}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.github.com/jennyballif/jennyballif.github.io/master/images/SMG6/egshells.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Eggshell geodes with different textures from different temperatures.&quot; style=&quot;width:600px !important&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the above picture, you can see eggshell geodes from six different jars. The green eggs on the far left were put into water that was luke-warm. It had cooled down almost to room temperature and you can see that the crystals are very small, almost like grains of sand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The eggs in the middle were placed into water that was still very warm, but not a temperature too hot to bathe in. Most of the crystals are the size of gravel and distinct from each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the blue eggs went into water that was nearly boiling. The alum solution had just come off the stove and after tempering the glass a bit, the hot liquid went straight into the jars and then the eggshells followed. All of the eggshells on the top row were seeded; I rubbed a little elmers glue onto the inside of the shell and sprinkled dry alum powder over them before putting them into the solution. The shells on the bottom row were not seeded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tip 2: Use distilled water&lt;/strong&gt;. If you live in an area with hard water, the dissolved calcium and magnesium ions that are already in solution will affect the crystal growth quite a bit. Even without hard water, distilled water helps you to get more of your solute to go into solution. Pick up a gallon of distilled water from the grocery store before you start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tip 3: All of these crystals will dissolve again in water&lt;/strong&gt;. That’s good news if you’d like to experiment and redo the projects again several times, because you can just boil up your crystals and reuse them. But if you’d like to keep them long term as an art project or decoration, be sure to coat them with a clear coating of nail polish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now, a few quick notes and recipes. You can also find the recipes on the foldable book at the bottom of the page:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;salt-crystals&quot;&gt;SALT CRYSTALS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In theory, you should be able to place a seed crystal into a saturated solution of salt water and grow an even larger crystal. In practice, I was never able to get this one to work. Each time I placed my seed crystal into solution, it dissolved, and I was left with an empty loop of floss or string like you see in the picture below. If you’re able to grow a large salt crystal, please leave a comment or send me a message. I’d love to see a picture!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
.image-wrapper{
  max-width:90%;
  height:auto;
  display:block;
  margin: auto;
}

.image-wrapper img{
  height:auto;
  display:block;
  text-align: center;
  margin: auto;
  max-width: 100%; 
}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.github.com/jennyballif/jennyballif.github.io/master/images/SMG6/saltcrystal.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;My salt crystals that dissolved.&quot; style=&quot;width:600px !important&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But for salt crystals all clumped together in a jar? These are easy. Just let salt water sit in a jar and wait. And wait. It requires a good amount of time, up to a month or more if you have a less concentrated solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;halocline-egg&quot;&gt;HALOCLINE EGG&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you make your halocline, be sure that the top layer of water doesn’t splash into the salt water too much. If you create currents or stick a spoon into the jar and mix it, then of course the salt and fresh water will mix and the halocline will disappear. But if you pour the fresh water in slowly and let the stream of water land on a spoon before it touches the salt water, then it should work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
.image-wrapper{
  max-width:90%;
  height:auto;
  display:block;
  margin: auto;
}

.image-wrapper img{
  height:auto;
  display:block;
  text-align: center;
  margin: auto;
  max-width: 100%; 
}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.github.com/jennyballif/jennyballif.github.io/master/images/SMG6/halocline.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Eggs in freshwater (left), resting on a halocline (middle), and salt water (right).&quot; style=&quot;width:600px !important&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After several hours, the salt water loses it’s cloudy appearance and it almost looks like a magic trick to see this egg hovering in the middle of the jar. The halocline layer is very stable. The eggs in the above picture had been sitting in the same positions (bottom, middle, top) for two weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;eggshell-geodes&quot;&gt;EGGSHELL GEODES&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the eggshells in the picture under tip 1, it looked like seeding did help to promote more uniform crystal growth. But in subsequent batches, I didn’t get very consistent results. Take the crystal below, for example, which had been seeded with alum and then placed in very hot water and grew crystals on only a few locations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
.image-wrapper{
  max-width:90%;
  height:auto;
  display:block;
  margin: auto;
}

.image-wrapper img{
  height:auto;
  display:block;
  text-align: center;
  margin: auto;
  max-width: 100%; 
}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.github.com/jennyballif/jennyballif.github.io/master/images/SMG6/largealum.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;An eggshell with an unusual growth of alum crystals.&quot; style=&quot;width:600px !important&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With hot water especially (which perhaps melts off the glue anyway?) I concluded that the texture of the eggshells plays an even bigger role than seeding. I think scratching the inside of the shell lightly would probably do just as much to promote crystal formation inside the shell as seeding it with dry alum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;suggested-recipe-makes-2-eggshell-geodes&quot;&gt;Suggested recipe (makes 2 eggshell geodes):&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2 pint-size mason jars&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2 eggshells&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2 2/3 cup water&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 1/3 cup alum&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Food coloring&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: the alum doesn’t incorporate much food coloring into its crystal structure, so if you want to see a tint of color to the crystals, you’ll want to add a lot of food coloring (think 20 plus drops). Most of the coloring will end up on the eggshell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;borax-snowflakes&quot;&gt;BORAX SNOWFLAKES&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Borax are good reliable crystals that grow quite easily. No need to seed your pipe cleaner in advance. The texture is rough enough that the crystals will grow all over it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;suggested-recipe-makes-1-large-pipe-cleaner-crystal&quot;&gt;Suggested recipe (makes 1 large pipe-cleaner crystal)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 quart-size mason jar&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 pipe cleaner&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;string or floss and a pencil to suspend the pipe cleaner&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 cup borax&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;4 cups water&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Food coloring&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bring to boil to dissolve the borax and pour into jar. Again, letting the solution cool in the pot first will produce a finer texture to the crystals, and putting it in hot will give you blockier and larger crystals. Use a lot of food coloring if you want to see a tint of color to the crystals (or for color you can rely on the colored pipe cleaner that you’ll be able to see through the crystals).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;rock-candy&quot;&gt;ROCK CANDY&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d recommend adding some flavoring to your rock candy, because the sugar flavor is somewhat overpowering when you make it plain. Lemon extract would be a good choice. You can find the recipe both below and in this 3 minute video:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
html,body        {height:100%;}
.vidwrapper      {width:100%; max-width: 600px; height:100%; margin:0 auto; background:#CCC; text-align: center}
.h_iframe        {position:relative; padding-top: 56%;}
.h_iframe iframe {position:absolute;top:0;left:0;width:100%; height:100%;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;vidwrapper&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;h_iframe&quot;&gt;
        &lt;iframe height=&quot;400&quot; width=&quot;2&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/oBJFuDobcWY&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;suggested-recipe-makes-2&quot;&gt;Suggested recipe (makes 2)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2 quart size mason jars&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2 cake pop sticks or popsicle sticks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2 coffee filters&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;6 cups sugar&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2 cups water&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;flavoring and food coloring (optional)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to grow rock candy as quickly as possible, you can use the fully saturated 8 cups of water to 2 cups of sugar. But this will crystalize very quickly (within a few hours), and if you leave it too long, you won’t be able to get it out of the jar. The ratio of 7 cups of sugar into 2 cups of water will usually be done by the end of one day, but 6 cups seems to be the right balance to me. It has the benefit of being able to see visible progress but progresses slowly enough that you’re not being in danger of having the crystals get away from you and get stuck to the jar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, like you saw in the short video above, making sugar gemstones is, in my opinion, and even better way to experiment with sugar crystals. This one does require some patience, because large size crystals take several weeks to grow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bath-bombs&quot;&gt;BATH BOMBS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Citric acid and epsom salts can be found in some grocery stores, but it’s probably easiest (as with the alum) to order them online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;suggested-recipe-makes-about-8-small-bath-bombs&quot;&gt;Suggested recipe (makes about 8 small bath bombs)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1/2 c baking soda&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1/3 c cornstarch&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1/4 c epsom salt&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1/4 c citric acid&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 Tbsp water&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 Tbsp oil (any kind)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;20 or so drops of essential oil&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a couple drops food coloring (optional)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mix the dry ingredients and wet ingredients in separate bowls. For the tablespoon of oil I recommend using whatever unsaturated cooking oil you have on hand (canola, olive, vegetable). If you’d like to purchase a nicer cosmetic oil (such as jojoba oil or castor oil), that’s a perfectly good option too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use a whisk to slowly combine the dry ingredients into the wet ingredients until the mixture has a sandy texture. You can pack the bathbombs with your hands into spheres or small bricks and let them sit for 48 hours, and they will work just fine. But if you want them to look like the type you’d find in a store, use small bath bomb molds. I thought plastic easter eggs would be a great hack for this – but it turns out that they’re almost impossible to get out of the eggs once you’ve packed them in and they’ve dried. I had to dump the whole egg in water and use the bath bomb to get it out. Just so you know. ;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That about covers it! If you’d like to preview the little foldable book that accompanies this guide, you can do so by scrolling through the pages in the viewer below. To print your own copy, just select your preferred size of paper: 8½ × 11, 11 × 17, A3 or A4. &lt;strong&gt;Don’t forget to print “Actual size.” Do not print “Fit to page” or the book won’t come out right.&lt;/strong&gt; To fold the book, either print the two-page document double sided, cut along the dotted lines, and then match the letters, or follow the instructions in this video: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=E0sS59oMBe0&amp;amp;t=3s&quot;&gt;How to Fold A Book from One Piece of Paper&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jenny Ballif</name></author><category term="science experiments" /><summary type="html">Science Mom’’s Guide to Water, Part 6</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Science Mom’s Guide to Water, Part 5</title><link href="http://localhost:4001/science-mom-s-guide-to-water-part-5" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Science Mom’s Guide to Water, Part 5" /><published>2017-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4001/science-mom-s-guide-to-water-part-5</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4001/science-mom-s-guide-to-water-part-5">&lt;h1 id=&quot;science-moms-guide-to-water-part-5&quot;&gt;Science Mom’’s Guide to Water, Part 5&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Water is so good at dissolving things, that it’s earned the label of “Universal Solvent.” But one thing water &lt;em&gt;doesn’t&lt;/em&gt; dissolve is oil. In Science Mom’s Guide to Water, Part 5, we explore why oil and water don’t mix with four investigations: Ocean in a bottle, Lava lamp, Oil lamp, and a grease fire explosion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
html,body        {height:100%;}
.vidwrapper      {width:100%; max-width: 600px; height:100%; margin:0 auto; background:#CCC; text-align: center}
.h_iframe        {position:relative; padding-top: 56%;}
.h_iframe iframe {position:absolute;top:0;left:0;width:100%; height:100%;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;vidwrapper&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;h_iframe&quot;&gt;
        &lt;iframe height=&quot;400&quot; width=&quot;2&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/KPjp2qg8SA4&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can preview the accompanying guide by scrolling through the pages in the viewer below. To print your own copy, just select your preferred size of paper: 8½ × 11, 11 × 17, A3 or A4. &lt;strong&gt;Don’t forget to print “Actual size.” Do not print “Fit to page” or the book won’t come out right.&lt;/strong&gt; To fold the book, either print the two-page document double sided, cut along the dotted lines, and then match the letters, or follow the instructions in this video: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=E0sS59oMBe0&amp;amp;t=3s&quot;&gt;How to Fold A Book from One Piece of Paper&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jenny Ballif</name></author><category term="science experiments" /><category term="Science" /><category term="Mom" /><category term="Guide" /><summary type="html">Science Mom’’s Guide to Water, Part 5</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Science Mom’s Guide to Water, Part 4</title><link href="http://localhost:4001/science-mom-s-guide-to-water-part-4" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Science Mom’s Guide to Water, Part 4" /><published>2017-03-20T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-03-20T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4001/science-mom-s-guide-to-water-part-4</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4001/science-mom-s-guide-to-water-part-4">&lt;h1 id=&quot;science-moms-guide-to-water-part-4&quot;&gt;Science Mom’s Guide to Water, Part 4&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Water is one of the few substances that expands when it freezes. And this expansion makes ice is less dense than liquid water, which means that ice floats! This is strange behavior when compared to how most other compounds behave. If you drop a piece of solid iron into liquid or molten iron, it will sink before it melts. Same thing happens when you drop frozen oil into liquid oil: the solid sinks. Most solids are more dense than their liquids.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
.image-wrapper{
  max-width:90%;
  height:auto;
  display:block;
  margin: auto;
}

.image-wrapper img{
  height:auto;
  display:block;
  text-align: center;
  margin: auto;
  max-width: 100%; 
}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.github.com/jennyballif/jennyballif.github.io/master/images/SMG4/FBThumbnail1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Cartoon depiction of ice floating.&quot; style=&quot;width:600px !important&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a few other elements and compounds that also expand when frozen (such as silicon,bismuth, gallium, geranium, and antimony). But a lot of these elements don’t ever occur naturally in their pure forms, so for all practical intents and purposes, water is just about the only thing we deal with that expands when frozen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To learn more about why and how water freezes, watch Science Mom’s Guide to Water, part 4:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
html,body        {height:100%;}
.vidwrapper      {width:100%; max-width: 600px; height:100%; margin:0 auto; background:#CCC; text-align: center}
.h_iframe        {position:relative; padding-top: 56%;}
.h_iframe iframe {position:absolute;top:0;left:0;width:100%; height:100%;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;vidwrapper&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;h_iframe&quot;&gt;
        &lt;iframe height=&quot;400&quot; width=&quot;2&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/4Y7SWqUJJ9A&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can preview the accompanying guide by scrolling through the pages in the viewer below. To print your own copy, just select your preferred size of paper: 8½ × 11, 11 × 17, A3 or A4. &lt;strong&gt;Don’t forget to print “Actual size.” Do not print “Fit to page” or the book won’t come out right.&lt;/strong&gt; To fold the book, either print the two-page document double sided, cut along the dotted lines, and then match the letters, or follow the instructions in this video: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=E0sS59oMBe0&amp;amp;t=3s&quot;&gt;How to Fold A Book from One Piece of Paper&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And join us next time for Science Mom’s Guide to Water, Part 5 [coming April, 2017], where we investigate why oil and water don’t mix.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jenny Ballif</name></author><category term="science experiments" /><category term="Water," /><category term="Science" /><category term="Mom" /><category term="Guide" /><summary type="html">Science Mom’s Guide to Water, Part 4</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Science Mom’s Guide to Water, Part 3</title><link href="http://localhost:4001/science-mom-s-guide-to-water-part-3" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Science Mom’s Guide to Water, Part 3" /><published>2017-02-07T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2017-02-07T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4001/science-mom-s-guide-to-water-part-3</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4001/science-mom-s-guide-to-water-part-3">&lt;h1 id=&quot;science-moms-guide-to-water-part-3&quot;&gt;Science Mom’s Guide to Water, Part 3&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Capillary action allows water to flow uphill, against the flow of gravity. It takes effect in small spaces and around things that water is attracted to. But water is attracted to a lot of things: plants, rocks, glass, plastic, most cloths and plenty of other materials too. This ability of water to move through small spaces has big effects in biology and geology, and it allows us to do some great science activities too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To learn more about capillary action and adhesion, watch Science Mom’s Guide to Water, part 3:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
html,body        {height:100%;}
.vidwrapper      {width:100%; max-width: 600px; height:100%; margin:0 auto; background:#CCC; text-align: center}
.h_iframe        {position:relative; padding-top: 56%;}
.h_iframe iframe {position:absolute;top:0;left:0;width:100%; height:100%;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;vidwrapper&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;h_iframe&quot;&gt;
        &lt;iframe height=&quot;400&quot; width=&quot;2&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/4OgcPI7S8_o&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can preview the accompanying guide by scrolling through the pages in the viewer below. To print your own copy, just select your preferred size of paper: 8½ × 11, 11 × 17, A3 or A4. &lt;strong&gt;Don’t forget to print “Actual size.” Do not print “Fit to page” or the book won’t come out right.&lt;/strong&gt; To fold the book, either print the two-page document double sided and follow the instructions on the back, or follow the instructions in this video: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=E0sS59oMBe0&amp;amp;t=3s&quot;&gt;How to Fold A Book from One Piece of Paper&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And join us next time for Science Mom’s Guide to Water, Part 4 [coming March, 2017], where we investigate why &lt;strong&gt;water expands when frozen&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jenny Ballif</name></author><category term="science experiments" /><category term="Siphons," /><category term="Paper" /><category term="Towels," /><category term="Water," /><category term="Food" /><category term="Coloring," /><category term="Capillary" /><category term="Action," /><category term="Adhesion" /><summary type="html">Science Mom’s Guide to Water, Part 3</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Science Mom’s Guide to Water, Part 2</title><link href="http://localhost:4001/science-mom-s-guide-to-water-part-2" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Science Mom’s Guide to Water, Part 2" /><published>2016-12-21T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2016-12-21T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4001/science-mom-s-guide-to-water-part-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4001/science-mom-s-guide-to-water-part-2">&lt;h1 id=&quot;science-moms-guide-to-water-part-2&quot;&gt;Science Mom’’s Guide to Water, Part 2&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Water has the strongest surface tension of any non-metalic fluid. So for most of the liquids we come in contact with, water is the surface tension champion. Whether you’re comparing it to oils and alcohols or hydrocarbons like gasoline and lighter fluid, water will stand above the crowd. Literally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
.image-wrapper{
  max-width:90%;
  height:auto;
  display:block;
  margin: auto;
}

.image-wrapper img{
  height:auto;
  display:block;
  text-align: center;
  margin: auto;
  max-width: 100%; 
}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.github.com/jennyballif/jennyballif.github.io/master/images/SMG2/SMG2blog1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Cartoon depiction of water as a solid, liquid, and a gas.&quot; style=&quot;width:600px !important&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Water forms beautiful domes on waxed paper while other liquids remain rather flat. We can poke those drops or try to squash them with our fingers, and (so long as our fingers are clean), the drops will keep their dome-like shape. But if we dip a toothpick in soap and touch them? Then the surface tension of the water changes dramatically:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
.image-wrapper{
  max-width:90%;
  height:auto;
  display:block;
  margin: auto;
}

.image-wrapper img{
  height:auto;
  display:block;
  text-align: center;
  margin: auto;
  max-width: 100%; 
}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.github.com/jennyballif/jennyballif.github.io/master/images/SMG2/SMG2blog2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Cartoon depiction of water as a solid, liquid, and a gas.&quot; style=&quot;width:600px !important&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the picture above, I touched every other drop with the soapy toothpick, and you can see how flat they got in comparison to their non-soapy neighbors! It doesn’t take very much soap to make a huge difference to the surface tension.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To learn more about why surface tension works and to see several fun investigations you can do with surface tension, watch Science Mom’s Guide to Water, Part 2:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
html,body        {height:100%;}
.vidwrapper      {width:100%; max-width: 600px; height:100%; margin:0 auto; background:#CCC; text-align: center}
.h_iframe        {position:relative; padding-top: 56%;}
.h_iframe iframe {position:absolute;top:0;left:0;width:100%; height:100%;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;vidwrapper&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;h_iframe&quot;&gt;
        &lt;iframe height=&quot;400&quot; width=&quot;2&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/OeYYiSsPf4I&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can preview the accompanying guide by scrolling through the pages in the viewer below. To print your own copy, just select your preferred size of paper: 8½ × 11, 11 × 17, A3 or A4. &lt;strong&gt;Don’t forget to print “Actual size.” Do not print “Fit to page” or the book won’t come out right.&lt;/strong&gt; To fold the book, either print the two-page document double sided and follow the instructions on the back, or follow the instructions in this video: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=E0sS59oMBe0&amp;amp;t=3s&quot;&gt;How to Fold A Book from One Piece of Paper&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And join us next time for Science Mom’s Guide to Water, Part 3 [coming February, 2017], where we investigate &lt;strong&gt;capillary action&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;adhesion&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jenny Ballif</name></author><category term="science experiments" /><summary type="html">Science Mom’’s Guide to Water, Part 2</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Science Mom’s Guide to Water, Part 1</title><link href="http://localhost:4001/science-mom-s-guide-to-water-part-1" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Science Mom’s Guide to Water, Part 1" /><published>2016-12-14T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2016-12-14T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4001/science-mom-s-guide-to-water-part-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4001/science-mom-s-guide-to-water-part-1">&lt;h1 id=&quot;science-moms-guide-to-water-part-1&quot;&gt;Science Mom’’s Guide to Water, Part 1&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Water is so abundant, we often take for granted how remarkable and unusual it is. Water is the &lt;strong&gt;only substance&lt;/strong&gt; on our planet that can exist naturally in all three states of matter: as a solid, a liquid, and a gas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
.image-wrapper{
  max-width:90%;
  height:auto;
  display:block;
  margin: auto;
}

.image-wrapper img{
  height:auto;
  display:block;
  text-align: center;
  margin: auto;
  max-width: 100%; 
}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.github.com/jennyballif/jennyballif.github.io/master/images/SMG1/SMG1a.png&quot; alt=&quot;Cartoon depiction of water as a solid, liquid, and a gas.&quot; style=&quot;width:600px !important&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gaseous water, or water vapor, is invisible. There’s always some of it in the air around us and we call it &lt;strong&gt;humidity&lt;/strong&gt;. The more water vapor in the air, the more humid it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only other things on earth that come close to existing in all three states of matter are mercury, acetic acid, and carbon dioxide. And while all three states of matter are &lt;strong&gt;possible&lt;/strong&gt; with each of these, they don’t occur &lt;strong&gt;naturally&lt;/strong&gt;. Water, on the other hand? It’s everywhere. Just look at this view of our world:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
.image-wrapper{
  max-width:90%;
  height:auto;
  display:block;
  margin: auto;
}

.image-wrapper img{
  height:auto;
  display:block;
  text-align: center;
  margin: auto;
  max-width: 100%; 
}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.github.com/jennyballif/jennyballif.github.io/master/images/SMG1/SMG1b.png&quot; alt=&quot;View of Pacific Ocean.&quot; style=&quot;width:800px !important&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oceans cover most of the earth’s surface, and so does another layer of water: clouds. At any given moment between 60 to 70% of the planet is under cloud cover. But as impressive as those facts are, they aren’t the only unique things about water. Water has seven other incredible properties:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
.image-wrapper{
  max-width:90%;
  height:auto;
  display:block;
  margin: auto;
}

.image-wrapper img{
  height:auto;
  display:block;
  text-align: center;
  margin: auto;
  max-width: 100%; 
}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.github.com/jennyballif/jennyballif.github.io/master/images/SMG1/SMG1c.png&quot; alt=&quot;Water's properties of cohesion, adhesion, and surface tension.&quot; style=&quot;width:600px !important&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
.image-wrapper{
  max-width:90%;
  height:auto;
  display:block;
  margin: auto;
}

.image-wrapper img{
  height:auto;
  display:block;
  text-align: center;
  margin: auto;
  max-width: 100%; 
}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.github.com/jennyballif/jennyballif.github.io/master/images/SMG1/SMG1d.png&quot; alt=&quot;Cartoon depiction of water being universal solvent and having a high specific heat.&quot; style=&quot;width:600px !important&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
.image-wrapper{
  max-width:90%;
  height:auto;
  display:block;
  margin: auto;
}

.image-wrapper img{
  height:auto;
  display:block;
  text-align: center;
  margin: auto;
  max-width: 100%; 
}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.github.com/jennyballif/jennyballif.github.io/master/images/SMG1/SMG1e.png&quot; alt=&quot;Cartoon depiction of water having capillary action and ice being less dense than liquid water.&quot; style=&quot;width:600px !important&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only are these attributes of water essential for life on earth—they’re the key to a lot of fun investigations and science experiments. So join me for SCIENCE MOM’S GUIDE TO WATER, where we learn about the incredible chemistry of water through hands-on activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our first video and guide we use three fun investigations to explore &lt;strong&gt;cohesion&lt;/strong&gt;—the ability of water molecules to stick to each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
html,body        {height:100%;}
.vidwrapper      {width:100%; max-width: 600px; height:100%; margin:0 auto; background:#CCC; text-align: center}
.h_iframe        {position:relative; padding-top: 56%;}
.h_iframe iframe {position:absolute;top:0;left:0;width:100%; height:100%;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;vidwrapper&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;h_iframe&quot;&gt;
        &lt;iframe height=&quot;400&quot; width=&quot;2&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/IsvHQon2IqQ&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can preview the accompanying guide by scrolling through the pages in the viewer below. To print your own copy, just select your preferred size of paper: 8½ × 11, 11 × 17, A3 or A4. &lt;strong&gt;Don’t forget to print “Actual size.” Do not print “Fit to page” or the book won’t come out right.&lt;/strong&gt; To fold the book, either print the two-page document double sided and follow the instructions on the back, or check my video: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=E0sS59oMBe0&amp;amp;t=3s&quot;&gt;How to Fold A Book from One Piece of Paper&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And join us next time for &lt;a href=&quot;https://jennyballif.com/science-mom-s-guide-to-water-part-2&quot;&gt;Science Mom’s Guide to Water, Part 2&lt;/a&gt;, where we investigate &lt;strong&gt;surface tension&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jenny Ballif</name></author><category term="science experiments" /><category term="experiments" /><category term="foldable" /><category term="video" /><summary type="html">Science Mom’’s Guide to Water, Part 1</summary></entry></feed>